welcome to cultivating wisdom with john
rovaki
unfortunately we are back down to the
single camera setup today
uh we hope to have that problem solved
off
by next week and back to the two camera
so i'm at this odd angle when i'm in the
sitting position
uh the camera will be more normal when i
move to the whiteboard
so i'm going to put my head down i hope
you don't consider this uh rude for
the reasons that we're primates and
we're supposed to look at each other etc
etc
uh so um a reminder that we're live
streaming
every saturday morning at 10 a.m eastern
eastern time the discord server is
continuing to have the daily meditation
sets i believe they sit
uh twice a day uh they do the moving
practices
uh uh they're starting to put together
the resources for doing the
philosophical
contemplative companionships um and so
uh amar and jason and i are working to
try and put together
a group of people uh drawn from the
sangha
by which we can film a demonstration of
how to do the philosophical
contemplative companionship practices
for you guys that's going to take a bit
of time
um we also want to put together a
compilation video to mark
the ending of the daily sits please send
a clip of no more than 10 seconds about
your experience as part of the sangha
community
to amarr a-m-m-a-r-m-r
at john vervicki one word dot com amar
john ricky dot com if you're joining us
for the first time don't be put off by
disorientation like i said we normally
have two cameras
it'll be better next time please see the
links in the description
i would strongly recommend you go
through the entire meditating with john
verveinke course
go and do lesson one right away do one
or two lessons every week
continue to meet with us on the saturday
saga
uh also uh consider joining the discord
server
i would ask everybody to please like
this stream decrease the visibility in
the youtube algorithm
um there will be a question period today
we're going to try and
not do what i did last time and make
sure there's a question period at the
end
please limit your questions to anything
from either one of the ecologies of
practices
uh the meditating genre vicky
the cultivating of wisdom um if you have
more general questions please come
to the general q a every third friday of
the month at 3 00
pm eastern time we had one yesterday and
it was really wonderful i wasn't feeling
very well
uh but the senior was uh there the
thing of the of the broader community
um and it was just really really
wonderful and i really appreciate that
okay so what we're going to do is we're
going to sit first
as always we will begin um with
chanting then we will go into silent set
we'll come out of the practice
potentially uh reciting the five
promises if you wish
i'll move to the white board um we'll go
through a review of what we talked about
with stoicism and then we'll come back
here and we will hopefully do
uh one of the first stoic practices i'm
going to talk about two main ones today
uh the cultivation of active
open-mindedness through self-examination
and the view from above as a meditative
con
as really a contemplative practice all
right so get yourself
in position please
set your phones on do not disturb and we
will begin together when i say begin
begin
oh
one
on
[Music]
one
on
[Music]
one
begin your silences
oh
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communitas
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
okay i'm going to move to the whiteboard
jason's going to adjust the camera
ah
so we're talking about stoicism and i
want to review
uh what we talked about last time and we
talked about of course how everything
comes from the pivotal figure of
socrates
and of course followed through um
we followed that line through epicurus
we will later follow a line through
uh plato uh but the uh one of the great
disciples that this line we're falling
through right now
is antisthenes um and his destinies
learned how to converse with himself
and then he taught a bunch of people
and then we got into diogenes and we
talked about diogenes in the cynics uh
this behavior that was uh intended to be
provocative of existential reframing
we talked about the what and disney's
talked about conversing with yourself we
of course talk all day long
and we do this because the brain's
relationship the relationship between
brains
and the brain's relationship to itself
or on continuum the into those two
poles interpenetrate mutually afford
mutually affect
each other in powerful ways and so this
is the idea that
excuse me cognition is not here
monological
it's dialogical and
of course untutored uh dialogue is
better than no dialogue
at all and we do so we do are in
constant dialogue with ourselves
and again untutored is better than not
having it at all because it gives us
powers
of reflection and self-direction etc but
we noted
that um without the untutored uh
dialogue you have problem of narrative
bias
um and you have the problem of uh
illumination things like that we talked
about that
so that inner dialogue can generate bad
judgment
and judgment is a crucial idea uh for
the
for uh the line coming out of intestines
so we took a look at the cynics
and we took a look at their diagnosis of
what was the nature of the bat judgment
and their diagnosis was
that we set our heart on the wrong thing
we set our heart on the wrong thing
um this relates to carol dweck's more
recent work on mindset
if you want to take a look at that and
we noted that this isn't a matter of
just believing
we didn't know that the original meaning
of belief believing was to set your
heart
for something to be beloved to you and
so for the cynics
the cause of our problem is we set our
hearts and what is created by social
convention
social construction rather than what is
natural or due to the natural or moral
law
so what did they practice they practice
obviously social renunciation they
rejected
the society that was the generator
social convention social construction
and they engaged in provocation to try
and wake people up to
that what they should set their hearts
on are the patterns generated by natural
and moral law and we talked about that
sort of existential reframing
we did the example of diogenes with the
lamp etcetera
now the cynics are deeply influential on
the stoics but the stoics
basically came to the conclusion to
summarize it they don't actually say
this explicitly in any one place
so i'm summarizing it on their behalf
the the cynics paid too much attention
to the
object of judgment rather than to the
process of judgment
and so the stoic zero in on the process
of judgment
the process of judgment is and we talked
about this before
when we did the meditation and
contemplation course
the process of judgment that they're
talking about is the process
of co-identification it's existential
mode
participation it's being in the having
mode being in the being mode
uh the eye the it the eye though that
kind of thing
and then we talked about an idea that
prom actually drew from the stoics
and we talked about it before especially
with relationship to contemplative
practices like meta
it's going to be a vital event to a
contemplative practice we're going to do
together today the view from above
and this was the story for addressing
modal confusion
uh the confusion of the having mode and
the b node mode
specifically the attempt to satisfy
being needs
within the having mode the starts go
very deep into this
into discerning discerning that this the
discipline of discernment right
discerning the modal confusion by
practicing
reflecting continuously
and in awareness not just in thought but
you know where it's reflecting on
what is in your control and this is one
of the
one of the three great stoics that you
need to read to practice stoicism
epic fetus on his encuradon the manual
for living
the books i recommend is get the manual
by epictetus at the meditations by
marcus aurelius
and get the letters uh from the stoic uh
by seneca
so uh what do what does epictetus point
out that
we are very confused about how much
control
uh we exercise they point out that we
have far
less control over the world than we
pretend
there's a deep pretentiousness they want
to challenge
uh the two things they point out are
what's called the proliferation of
consequences
that when i try to do good even when i
completely honestly intend to do good
uh there are all kinds of ways in which
are the consequences open up um in ways
the side effects unanticipated by me um
and
that can be very overwhelming the other
is the fatality of all things that
the universe is 99.9 percent not
hospitable to human beings it runs
largely of its own accord
and that 90 so there's about a 99.9
percent of the universe
it does not care about your narrative
it does not and so um things are going
to happen outside of our narrative
identity and our narrative
and the idea is that the proliferation
of consequences
and the fatality of all things uh cause
us fear
causes frustration tells us deep
disappointment
so notice how the stoics have picked up
from the cynics the idea that we're
deeply disappointed because we set our
hearts
and right on the wrong things the stoics
say no but it's more that we set our
hearts in the wrong way
not better sorry
i hope that were people still able to
hear yeah
okay good so i don't have to repeat i'm
sorry about that i didn't realize those
i was brushing up against the mic
very often uh so they've picked up
uh from the cynics the idea of deep fear
and frustration of disappointment
uh because of heart setting um but
unlike the cynics they don't put so
as much emphasis they talk a bit about
the importance of the
object that you set a heart on but
they're much more about how
we are doing this and so they recommend
that we pay attention to what is
actually in our control what is most in
our control
the stoics tend to talk about this as a
dichotomy i see it more
as a continuum with one pole what is
most under control i don't think it's
even completely in our control the way
they sometimes claim
but what is most in control is our
judgment and then
right there are things right and then as
we move towards that aspect of the world
that's completely beyond our control
and so there's this sliding continuum
but the idea is what is most in our
control is our judgment
judgment here again doesn't mean the
right the um
just this making of statements it has
much more to do with what we find
relevant what we find salient how we
identify things how we do the
co-identification process how we set up
that agent arena co-identification
co-determination process
and so the stoics talked about prososh
which is very similar to buddhist
notions of mindfulness
this is paying attention to how you pay
attention because attention
is where you're setting your heart on
things in the sense of
how you are finding things relevant
salient
how you're identifying them one way in
which you right in which
the stories are really zeroing in on one
way you identify
things and one and thereby make them
salient and relevant to you is
your judgment about how much they are
under your control
how much they are under your control
and the idea here is that
people need to realize
that they are deeply confused they're
deeply confused
because the judgments of the meaning
again not in the sense of a sentence but
in terms of the relevance
the salience and the identity the
meaning of the thing
is fused with the fact of the thing
and people confuse confuse
that because the meaning of a thing is
largely
uh something that's under their control
that they can
control the thing but they don't
distinguish the two
okay they misjudge that they have a
greater control
over things than they actually do
now that that was only the things the
stoics say that would be ah
but what they say is right if you don't
if you
pull them apart if you don't have them
any longer confused
what you realize is you have much
greater control
over the meaning of things than you
previously realized
and most of your frustration
not all but most of your frustration
fear and disappointment has to do with
the meaning of events
rather than the events themselves and
this is a central tenet
of what's known as cognitive behavioral
therapy one of the
most evidence-based therapies we have
right now
and what the stoics are trying to do is
get us into a state
where by exercising good judgment
about the meaning of things we can
afford reciprocal opening we can
remember the being mode
we can afford reciprocal opening with
things and we can get
into what they call flowing with nature
the state of joy
joy is the most important emotion
for stoicism and contrary to what people
think stoicism is not about
being dour and stiff upper lip just
going on right the point about stoicism
is to flow with nature and to experience
as much joy as possible
joy is not the same thing as pleasure
there is that sense
of being in
participating in reciprocal opening and
coming into an ever deepening right
relationship with yourself to others
and to the world it's a very very
powerful thing
uh to uh to experience
joy so this is another thing that
we need to talk about briefly the stoics
make a distinction
between passion
and emotion this is
these are modern terms these aren't
exactly the terms the stomach use but
they're close to what we're talking
about here
so they you they use the analogy of
walking down a hill
so think of the word motion so when
you're walking downhill
right that you're in motion and
if you are walking wisely you can flow
with the terrain
and you can actually get into enjoyment
passion is like when you start running
down the hill
we talk about the way our mind can run
away with itself or run away from us
right it's just my imagination once
again running away right
song by the temptations so when you're
running down a hill
you lose the capacity to adjust
your right you fall into a process that
is now
like taking away your ability to adjust
and to adapt
you fall out of sync with your terrain
and you're very very liable
to trip and fall and hurt yourself so
the point is not to be emotionless to
have no
affect the point is to get into
proper discernment proper judgment so
that you are always experiencing emotion
rather than passion and that those
emotions ultimately facilitate you
flowing with nature and getting into two
things
simultaneously enjoyment
which isn't pleasure as i've tried to
explain and encouragement
because the idea is if you have a true
understanding what is in your control
and what is not in your control then
that encourages you that gives you the
courage to keep going
it gives you the resources to put to
deal with frustration
and fear and disappointment so the idea
here is
we want to train our relevance machinery
our ability to determine what's relevant
sailing at the identity of things
so instead of it happening mindlessly
automatically
and reactively we want it to happen
reflectively
rationally and reliably
because we want uh what we find relevant
and how we find it relevant
to track what is real we want to walk
down the hill
in flowing enjoyment rather than
run down the hill falling and falling
again and again
so the idea here is we have to overcome
self-deception because self-deception
is primarily when our meaning making
machinery
is making things fall out of sync
with nature where right out of sync with
the patterns of intelligibility the
patterns by which we make sense
of the world ourselves and each other
and for the stoics
that involves three things logic
which basically this is the practice of
disciplining judgment
so it's not what we mean by formal logic
although the stoics
did some significant advances in formal
logic coming up with hypothetical
ethics where ethics is the disciplining
of impulse
and uh physics which
um is is what it overlaps with what we
call physics
but it also overlaps um
in in the sense of
getting very clear about pulling apart
how things are from how we desire them
to be
so and the logic there is more like
psychological
it has to do with more figuring out the
logos of the psyche
and the idea here is that logos of the
psyche is ultimately
our inner dialogues our inner dialogue
and that
if we get better at managing that inner
deal logos
we will better grasp the logos the
organizing principles of the psyche
and then we can then use that to
get a proper view of things so as to
properly discipline desire and we will
be able to deal with our impulses
um in an appropriate manner through our
ethical training so these are the three
pillars
of stoic rationality the three pillars
of stoic rationality
so you primarily do this
by the practice of internalizing
socrates
internalizing socrates stoicism is
basically the religion
the philosophy of internalizing socrates
in order to cultivate wisdom and virtue
each virtue is a way of being wise in
this particular situation so there's two
components i talked about this yesterday
of wisdom
this is sophia this is grasping
like grasping the logos this is grasping
the principles
that organize and govern things and then
phromesis
and we we say this but we forget how
deep it is putting it into practice
virtue is the beauty of wisdom virtue it
so virtue is how
in this situation i very best
do what is most wise so in this
situation to be wise in this situation
is to be kind
or to be honest or perhaps to be honest
and kind perhaps to be courageous
here perhaps to be you know uh resistant
to evil here
right so what you're always trying to do
when you're internalizing socrates is
you're trying to internalize these two
aspects so
this is what we you know what we are
cultivating
in so far as we're being scientific in
the very broad sense
and this is what we're cultivating when
we're being practical again in a much
deeper sense than we normally
mean day by day these are both terms for
wisdom by the way
both terms for wisdom so we internalize
socrates
and this is an inherently perspectival
process
it's the process by which we put
principles into practice
how does internalization look let's do
this again
here's some problem here's one of my
sons when they're younger
looking at the problem here i'm an adult
so remember
as the child is to the adult
the adult is to the sage we've already
talked about this but just reminding you
and i have a perspective on the problem
right that not only is on the problem
but on my son's perspective
this whole model of internalization
comes from vygotsky
one of the greatest of the developmental
psychologists and what
my son does perhaps it was jason when he
was younger
is he imitates me
so in addition
in addition imitates in addition to
trying to solve the problem
but jason is imitating me looking at him
and what he does is he keeps imitating
that
higher order perspective so here's his
first person perspective and
to him for me it's first person but to
him
it's a third person perspective
so he keeps in right he keeps imitating
and
imitating that and imitating that and
imitating that
until eventually he can do it for
himself without me being around
and he gets better and better and as
he's doing it with me i correct him and
correct him until eventually
he makes the ability to take that
perspective on
himself a property of his own cognition
this is how we get what's called
metacognition
this is your ability to step back and
become aware of your own cognition
but this stokes called prosh pay
attention to how you're paying attention
we of course broaden it um when we're
talking about it in cognitive science
but that's not really relevant right now
so what we want to do is
we and this is really powerful this
meta-perspectival ability
this matter perspectival ability when we
did the wisdom consensus paper this is
one of the core features
meta perspectival ability right this is
one of the core
features of wisdom why
because this is this is how you afford
self-transcendence when i'm
in this perspective i can't see the
biases of that perspective from within
it
and i also can't take on longer term
goals that are fall outside the scope of
this perspective
but by doing this i can see the biases
from a higher order perspective i can
see the biases and the inadequacies
of a lower order perspective we
literally transcend
ourselves by internalizing other people
so uh the person who put together the
task force ear broken
has all this evidence for example if
people if you have people describe a
problem
think about this think about this when
we do the view from above think about
what i'm going to say when we do the
view from above
right when you have people just send me
a problem like really emission and they
will almost always describe it from the
first person perspective
and then you say okay now i want you to
redescribe the problem
but from a third person perspective
somebody from the outside how somebody
from the outside would describe it and
then when they do that
they go oh and they have insights and
they have realization and they
often find a way of breaking out they
become wiser
they see what needs to be done they
activate the appropriate virtue
that needs to be uh brought in they
start to see through
previous self-deception so we want to
internalize
the sage and what that's going to give
us right is
we're going to do perspectival practice
for that
and when we do that we get
self-knowledge
which is not your autobiographical
knowledge
it's not your autobiographical narrative
self that's
and uh right and i'll use these two
axes to talk about this
i'm almost done and then we can go into
the view from above
your autobiographical this is your
horizontal
sense of identity this is how you're
pursuing
fame and power which are largely
pursuits
that confuse what's right the meaning of
things with the thing
and cause you to be self-deceived about
how much control you can exercise
but when you pursue fame and power
instead the kind of self-knowledge that
you get is
vertical it's ontological it's right if
your autobiography is a story
the ontological the vertical is like the
owner's manual you're trying to figure
out
uh the um the functions
by which you're set you're trying to
figure out the logos
of your psyche you're trying to figure
out the functions the structural
functional organization
by which it works so what you're trying
to do
here is this is largely the
project right of self-transcendence
and so that brings us into the final
component of this
the stoics ask well what should you
when you're transcending you're aspiring
you're trying to become
right something other than you are
you're self-transcending
you're internalizing the sage and of
course you're
you're aspiring and in a certain manner
but isn't that setting your heart on
something
you can hear like a cynic voice in there
and so like the cynics the stoics do pay
attention to the objects
right um of our aspiration the
object so that we set our heart so we're
setting our heart upon
our future self isn't that dangerous
isn't that the person that's doing fame
doing the same thing and so how you set
yourself
how you set your heart right and in what
way
you're setting your heart upon your
future self are really crucial
uh to the stoics so the stories say you
should always you should
and then you can hear the cynics again
here you should always set your heart
on that which is always good
is pleasure always good no it can really
screw you up badly
fame always good no i'm really messing
up his power always good no it often
corrupts
very often bad they even challenge the
epicureans of it this is is friendship
always good
yeah there seems to be time when
friendship can
uh really go awry
just friendship in a general sense and
so what the stoics uh
say is well what is always good
and they say well what's always good is
virtue and then you say about sometimes
i don't know which virtue
to apply and so they say yeah you're
right so what you really are saying
is that you're pointing to the fact that
a virtue is always the beauty of wisdom
that what what's always good is wisdom
because wisdom is what will always
help us to set our heart in the proper
way and you see how this sort of circles
back on itself
and what the stories are saying is set
your heart
on becoming the wisest person you can
internalizing the sage because wisdom is
always good
because right being able to put
principles into practice in the best
possible way with the
from the most rational in this broadest
sense frame of mind
is always good doesn't mean it's always
pleasurable
but pleasure isn't always good but it's
always good in that it is what is always
going to make your life
the most meaningful it can be and make
you the best possible person
can be so the stoics have two
you know two core kinds of
practices one is
uh practices of rational judgment
and aspiration
so you have to engage in some
fundamental practices of
self-examination
and then practices of
self-transformation
so the biggest practice here we've
talked about this before is active
open-mindedness
this is the practice i'll mention these
again
get one or all of these books you know
this but i'll put this i will put the uh
it's in the description you want this
book biased
um or the 25 cognitive biases
or cognitive biases the pocket reference
books
and what i do is i try to start every
day after i've done my practices i read
about a bias
i reflect upon it i think about it i try
and remember times when i engaged in it
and
um and then throughout the day and then
at the end of the day
i have my journal and at the end of the
day
what i do is i do this i look for any
vice that i committed any virtue that i
omitted any bias that i remember
engaging in the confirmation bias or
fundamental attribution error
self-centeredness and then i also
remember
so copy i also remember
any virtue that i clearly brought into
play
a situation where i was wiser than i
normally am
in any virtue i brought into play and do
that every day and every day and
slowly slowly this is called prochiron
this is keeping things ready to hand
this is you slowly slowly let this
permeate and percolate
and more and more you start to notice
the ways
in which you are engaging in
self-deception
ways in which you're being foolish now
if you just did that that would be like
oh
right that'd be like protestant guilt or
something that's why it's also important
to do these practices
because these practices are your
response these are the practices
that say to you right now this is what
you can do
to get better so that you can aspire
properly
and we're going to use we're going to do
about five
minutes or so right now of one of these
practices
so this is a practice that is designed
to transform
your you your perspective remember how
internalization is a pes
perspectival transformation if you get a
chance i have a talk
on youtube called the view from above in
which i go into this in greater detail
if you want sort of more of
the philosophy and the cognitive science
behind it but right now i'm going to sit
down jason's going to come and change
the camera again
and i'm going to talk you through uh the
view from above
so here the camera hang actually
actually works as i'm doing the view
from above
but you'll forget it's not good for me
with my ears to tilt my head up a lot so
i'll try and keep it um straight
throughout
so what i want to do is we'll just take
a minute or so
quiet do a very brief but find the core
four
like you've been doing it long enough
you should be able to get a sense of
being centered
uh have your basic root basic flow on
your focus
take a minute or two we'll say we'll be
in silence for a minute or two
and then i'm going to talk you through
like walk you through
the view from above practice okay so a
minute or two of silence first
uh
while keeping your eyes closed imagine
yourself
that's exactly where you are the room
that you're in
imagine it around you you're at the
center of that perspective
that's only natural
imagine that you're in exactly the place
that you're in
very gently imagine yourself at least
your
mind floating up up above
in the room the roof of your room
becoming transparent and you can see
into that room from above perhaps you
still see your body
sitting in the meditation posture
imagine yourself gently no fear
rising higher
you can see the entire city or
countryside
where you're living you see the house or
the building
that you're in your body's in but you
can see now the entire city
the countryside
now rise up even higher very gently
no jarring completely fine
now you can see entire country that you
belong to
spread out below you
take a moment to really dwell in this
notice how your sense of what's salient
and relevant
and what's important is shifting
the sense of self is even shifting
now rise up gently
no problem with any of this until you're
now seeing the whole earth
beneath you
very gently dwell here
note the transformation in your sense of
what's relevant
what's salient your sense of self
now even for even further and farther
so you're way back you're looking at the
entire solar system
you're starting to feel like you're no
one in particular
and you're nowhere in particular
settle into that try to enjoy it
now pull back back
further and further until you're seeing
the galaxy
that the solar system is within
now you're no one and you're nowhere
what's salient and relevant in your
sense of self are very different
now it's like there's a time machine
it's not just this moment now you're not
pulling back in space you're pulling
back in time
you can see back to the beginning of
time the beginning of the universe
and forward
far into the future
now you're not only no one and nowhere
you know when
savor this
notice the alteration and what things
how things feel
relevant salient what your sense of self
is
now slowly and paying attention to how
what's relevant and salient the
identities of things the boundary
sense of self change as you do this
slowly come back
slowly come back into seeing the solar
system
back in the present moment as well
so they come back to seeing the earth
and you feel things taking shape
tightening
the sense of self sense of the moment
what's important changing
now see the country that you belong to
now the city
now the building
i'll come into seeing the room
now reimagine yourself where you are
but remember what it was like to be no
one
know where know when
try to integrate those two together feel
them deeply together
like stereoscopic vision one eye is
seeing you
you hear now the other eye is seeing
that no one nowhere
no when
let them talk to each other let them
dialogue
okay slowly come out of your practice
so you can do that a little bit longer
especially when you're sort of at the
apex of the view from above you can hang
out there longer
but remember to right that that we're
gonna be not just doing the motion in
the imagination it's much more important
to pay attention
to use that as a platform by which you
are becoming aware of and
training the transformation of judgment
a perspectival judgment a perspective
taking what you find relevant and
salient the identities
that that are being assigned and assumed
and remember when you come back down to
see that transformation in reverse
and then use that memory of the
transformation up
and the transformation down to create a
stereoscopic vision
of you so for me i hear now
and no one nowhere
no when seeing the two together
seeing the two together and that way you
are
getting this capacity to take a very
powerful kind of
higher order perspective on yourself
enhance your medical respective
cognition
and enhance your capacity for
self-transcendence
and learn it learning deeply
to discern the difference between things
and the narratives that we assigned
things
okay so we're going to take about five
minutes or so for a few questions
um so uh deborah uh
wagstaff asked uh so good to see you
john how was
your sit today uh um it was uh
very good thank you for asking um
my ear is still bothering me for those
of you who were here yesterday at the q
a
but thank you for asking i do that both
sits
the first set and then the stoic sit
which is a contemplative practice
it's very much like meta and that it's a
reciprocal opening
uh process but it's much more
aspirational
than that but both sides were very good
thank you for asking
uh mark do the books contain more
information on how many rounds i have
two of them
on the way so far i think mark's
referring to
uh questions about the philosophical
contemplative companionship
um and the first book by the half talks
about
how many rounds i recommend a four 4x4 i
recommend
the half has other things but i've done
lots of participant observation
lots of groups i think four people
committing to four rounds
is really quite optimal that's what i
would recommend julian
gray can you please demonstrate
philosophical chanting
um so we will do that when we film
uh the so because ruminatio is
part of uh the the practice of
philosophical contemplative
companionship so we will film
uh we will film us doing uh
philosophical chanting so that that's
definitely coming
uh sheranio uh banerjee how to read
something if that stay present
while strained away in thoughts um
that's a tricky one that's part of i
mean there's there's dif
i mean you should read um
you should be reading at times for
different purposes right sometimes
you're reading for information
and then you read it for transformation
when you're reading for transformation
the way
of doing what you're talking about is to
do the lectio divina practice
that i've talked um but when you're
waiting for information then what you
have to do
is you have to uh you have to do soft
vigilance
you have to constantly be thinking about
trying to like it's like the meditative
practice trying to see what is new in
the text
what are the connections um so uh trying
to dialogue with the text
underline the text make notes uh ask
pause that sounds like but that'll slow
me down
and that's the ego trick right actually
if you look like you're slowing down to
note things to
do practice soft vigilance uh to
constantly renew your interest to make
notes
that will actually speed up your reading
because you will not be distracted as
much you are more likely to get in the
flow state than you
remember better what you're reading
while you're reading
pleasure the doubt that's brad it's good
to uh
it's good we haven't talked in a bit
brett it's it's good to have
communication with you
uh for those of not for those not
familiar with the works or cultural
historical context of the author
can you give tips for how to put oneself
in the author's perspective
uh so it's a good idea
this is actually it's a very good idea
for people to do some preliminary
um so when the facilitator chooses who
the reading
who the author is going to be to give a
forewarning and people to do do
a little bit of preliminary study this
is something i hadn't mentioned before
and i should have and that's a mistake
on my part so thank you brett for
this correction it's very important to
get some sense
of the historical context like you know
just a quick wikipedia scanning
because again um that's the uh that
that's very very
helpful uh but trying to pick up on even
your intuitive sense of the person
uh from the text so relying on your
intuition to try and get a sense
of what that person is like from the
text
is also valuable so historical education
online intuition
and again that can you have to also rely
on the convergence of
uh that different people bring to the
text
for actually invoking the presence of
the author
uh marco feb i often say that stoicism
gives us a how
but know why most seem to agree comments
um
so um like i tried to um say i think
stoicism does give us the why um but
it's often not well understood
uh there's the the um the why of
stoicism
is enjoyment and encouragement and
flowing with nature and the idea is to
live the kind of life
that has the most of that which is
always good
so the stoic answers to what is what is
the good life is very it sounds like a
very simple answer but i think it's a
very profound answer
the good life is the life that has the
most in it of what is most often
reliably good
what is most often reliably good is
wisdom where wisdom isn't mean just
saying wise things are having advice
but that discernment that puts us into
enjoyment
that puts us into a right relationship
with ourselves with each other
and the world a rational in the broader
sense of rational
right relationship that is enjoyed and
not pleasured
but enjoyed for its own sake because
that is
the good life that's the why um
so pleasure of doubt uh some have voiced
the concern that the philosophical
fellowship practice is too advanced for
most people on
discord that many haven't yet got down
uh prerequisite skills one and two
do you think it's probably conductive
for those without an established
practice and other skills you've taught
to move ahead with this news practice
is there harm in just jumping in um so
what i've seen
i actually see that the concern that
people are voicing is a very legitimate
serve
for the practice of dialectic which is a
neoplatonic practice
uh lahav and i agree with him argues
that philosophical contemplative
companionship can be started sort of
off the street all it requires is that
people have
good faith now that being said i do
think having that you shouldn't do the
practice
if you haven't had some experience with
the core four
of the mindfulness practice finding your
center root flow and focus
and some basic practice with lectio
divina so i sort of split the difference
with with
the half i think you should have that
the core four of mindfulness
and lexia davina in hand and then you
can take up the philosophical
contemplative companionship
i would say that until you've done the
philosophical contemplative
companionship you really shouldn't be
undertaking
uh the practice of dialectic now i do
things where i get people to practice
the dialectic
and uh and that's still helpful
um but those are much more like you know
the clinical trials in an experiment
experimental clinical trials you're
trying to figure out um
a practice i think when once you're in
the
existential frame that there should be a
pedagogical program
where you start with philosophical
contemplative companionships
and then you move into something um
intermediate uh perhaps like the
anti-debate
um and like which is a very stoic kind
of thing to do and then we move into the
neoplatonic practice
of dialectic but there's more of that uh
coming um i just wanted to remind people
that just like i recommended a book on
practice i recommend getting this book
we're going to be going through this
book so going forward on saturday sega
as we continue the high school of
stoicism we're then of course making use
of some of the suggestions in the clone
of
read mclean it's good it's helpful it's
valuable uh but
we're going to be relying on this book
as we do more and more
of the spiritual exercises um and you'll
see how they plug into the the logic the
physics and the ethics
so that's everything i think uh for uh
going forward
um again i apologize for the sort of odd
angle
at some point amar and jason are are
working on it they're putting
some more work on this weekend to get us
back to the tube camera
without all that that some of that
lagging that we had and as always i want
to thank amar and jason for all the work
they're doing behind the scenes making
this all
possible please subscribe to the channel
to be notified of the next video
also follow me please on twitter for any
updates about these streams
invite others who might benefit by
sharing this series
uh definitely join the discord server to
chat with others to sit with others
to start some of these group practices
reminder that we're doing this the
saturday sangha
every saturday 10 a.m eastern time
so let's remember
that a conduited practice is more
important than sheer quantity of
practice
and that we want to hold ourselves not
to a harsh perfectionism
but to a standard of virtuous friendship
by which we better
in a more discerning fashion deal logos
with ourselves
and with others because there is no
enemy
worse than your own mind and body but
there's no friend no ally no
philosophical companion
on the path better than your own
dialogical mind and body
be lamps unto yourselves and to each
other take care everyone
keep practicing i'll see you
next saturday
i